<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Halal Hustle Handbook RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[A blog of things I've learned throughout my career.]]></description><link>https://sadat21.github.io/blog</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 19:45:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[How to Convert CAD to USD to Purchase US Stocks]]></title><description><![CDATA[Converting CAD to USD to buy US stocks or ETFs can be expensive due to currency conversion fees. Many institutions charge a 1-2% fee on top…]]></description><link>https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-10-01-spus-hlal/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-10-01-spus-hlal/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Converting CAD to USD to buy US stocks or ETFs can be expensive due to currency conversion fees. Many institutions charge a 1-2% fee on top of the exchange rate, which can be a huge fee if you are converting a large sum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best ways to avoid these fees is by using &lt;strong&gt;Norbert’s Gambit&lt;/strong&gt;. In this guide, I’ll walk you through how to use Norbert’s Gambit on Questrade to efficiently convert CAD to USD and purchase US-listed ETFs like SPUS or HLAL within a Tax-Free Savings Account (TFSA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norbert&apos;s Gambit costs a fixed fee of two trades (~20 CAD as of writing today) no matter how much you are converting. For example, if you are converting $2000 CAD to USD, the fee is $20 CAD. If you are converting $10,000 CAD to USD, the fee is still $20 CAD. This makes Norbert&apos;s Gambit very cost-effective for large amounts of money. If you were to convert $10,000 CAD to USD using a traditional method, you would be charged a 1-2% fee on top of the exchange rate, which would be $100-$200 CAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason we are not using Wealthsimple for this process is because as of writing this post, they do not support Norbert&apos;s Gambit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quwstrade UI (User Interface) is always changing so I&apos;ll try to keep the steps generic enough to be applicable to any version of the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 1: Open a Questrade Account&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started, you need a Questrade account if you don’t already have one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.questrade.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Questrade website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When creating your Questrade account, be sure to use my referral code &lt;strong&gt;745627973479086&lt;/strong&gt; to get a welcome bonus!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose the account type you want to open. For this guide, we will focus on a &lt;strong&gt;Tax-Free Savings Account (TFSA)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill out the personal details such as name, address, and employment information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload the necessary identification documents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submit your application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questrade typically approves accounts within a few days. Once you’re approved, you can log in and move to the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 2: Open a TFSA Account&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you didn’t open a TFSA during the signup process, you can do so after logging into your Questrade account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TFSA allows for tax-free growth, making it an excellent option for long-term investing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 3: Fund Your Account with CAD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your TFSA is open, you’ll need to fund it with CAD to start the Norbert’s Gambit process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are multiple methods on how to fund your account. Choose the one that works best for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 4: Buy DLR.TO (Horizons US Dollar Currency ETF)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To perform Norbert’s Gambit, we use an ETF called DLR.TO. This ETF trades in CAD and tracks the US dollar, allowing us to convert CAD to USD without paying the usual currency conversion fees. Instead, we pay a trading fee when purchasing DLR.TO, and another when selling DLR.U.TO (the USD variant). This usually ends up being $20 CAD overall. Therefore Norberts Gambit is only worth it if you are converting a large amount of money (&gt;$2000) since the trading fee is fixed at $20 CAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the &lt;strong&gt;Trading&lt;/strong&gt; section in your Questrade account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for the ticker symbol &lt;strong&gt;DLR.TO&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy an amount of DLR.TO that matches how much CAD you want to convert to USD. For example, if you want to convert $5,000 CAD to USD, buy $5,000 worth of DLR.TO shares.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select &lt;strong&gt;Market&lt;/strong&gt; as the order type if you want to buy the ETF at the current market price, or &lt;strong&gt;Limit&lt;/strong&gt; if you want to set a specific price. I recommend using &lt;strong&gt;Market&lt;/strong&gt; to ensure the trade goes through quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submit your order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might take a few minutes to a few days for the order to be filled, depending on the market conditions and whether you placed a market or limit order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 5: Journal DLR.TO to DLR.U.TO (USD Variant)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve purchased DLR.TO, you need to &quot;journal&quot; it to the USD version, DLR.U.TO. Questrade doesn&apos;t have an automatic way to do this online, so you’ll have to contact customer support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a support live chat (preferred) or call Questrade’s customer service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask them to &lt;strong&gt;journal your DLR.TO shares to DLR.U.TO&lt;/strong&gt;. This process will convert your CAD-traded shares to USD-traded shares of the same ETF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The journal process typically takes 1-2 business days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 6: Sell DLR.U.TO for USD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the shares are journaled, you can sell DLR.U.TO to get USD in your TFSA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to your Questrade account and search for &lt;strong&gt;DLR.U.TO&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell your shares of DLR.U.TO.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will now have USD in your TFSA, ready to purchase US stocks or ETFs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 7: Buy US-listed ETFs (SPUS or HLAL)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With USD in your account, you can now buy US-listed ETFs like SPUS (a Shariah-compliant ETF following the S&amp;#x26;P 500) or HLAL (Wahed Invest’s Shariah-compliant ETF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the &lt;strong&gt;Trading&lt;/strong&gt; section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for the ticker symbol &lt;strong&gt;SPUS&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;HLAL&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place an order to buy the ETF of your choice using the USD you’ve converted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confirm the trade.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norbert’s Gambit is a great way to minimize currency conversion fees when investing in US stocks or ETFs through Questrade. With a bit of patience and some understanding of the process, you can save significantly over time especially if you are converting large amounts of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure to monitor your contributions to stay within the &lt;strong&gt;TFSA contribution limits&lt;/strong&gt; to avoid penalties. Learn more about TFSA contribution limits on my post about &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2024-09-24-halal-investing/&quot;&gt;Guide to Investing with Islamic Principles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out a very comprehensive guide on Norbert&apos;s Gambit &lt;a href=&quot;https://wealthsavvy.ca/norberts-gambit-questrade/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to Buy Your First Stock]]></title><description><![CDATA[Here's a quick step-by-step guide on how to open up your WealthSimple account and purchase your first stock. Wealthsimple is a great…]]></description><link>https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-09-30-wshr/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-09-30-wshr/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s a quick step-by-step guide on how to open up your WealthSimple account and purchase your first stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wealthsimple is a great platform for beginners because it&apos;s easy to use and has a low barrier to entry since there are no fees for purchasing/selling Canadian stocks and ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UI (User Interface) is always changing so I&apos;ll try to keep the steps generic enough to be applicable to any version of the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open a Wealthsimple account&lt;/strong&gt; using my referral code &lt;strong&gt;VZP-FW&lt;/strong&gt;. It’ll give both of us a small bonus! Link to Wealthsimple &lt;a href=&quot;https://wealthsimple.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open a TFSA account&lt;/strong&gt;. TFSA stands for &lt;strong&gt;Tax-Free Savings Account&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a special account where you don’t have to pay any tax on any gains made within the account. However, there is a limit on how much you can contribute. You unlock more contribution room on January 1st each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: If you turned 18 in 2023, your contribution room for that year would be $6,500. For 2024, the contribution limit has increased to &lt;strong&gt;$7,000&lt;/strong&gt;, giving you a total of &lt;strong&gt;$13,500&lt;/strong&gt; in contribution space if you haven’t yet contributed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check past contribution limits on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/services/tax/individuals/topics/tax-free-savings-account/contributions.html&quot;&gt;CRA website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always make sure you don’t exceed your contribution limit, or you’ll face fees from the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; You can withdraw money from a TFSA without penalties, but you won’t be able to re-contribute that amount until the following year when the limit refreshes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: Let&apos;s say you have &lt;strong&gt;$13,500&lt;/strong&gt; in your TFSA, and in &lt;strong&gt;June 2024&lt;/strong&gt;, you decide to withdraw &lt;strong&gt;$5,000&lt;/strong&gt; for an emergency. You can withdraw the money without any penalties, but you cannot re-contribute that &lt;strong&gt;$5,000&lt;/strong&gt; until &lt;strong&gt;January 1st, 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, when your TFSA limit resets. In 2025, you would get back the &lt;strong&gt;$5,000&lt;/strong&gt; you withdrew, plus the new contribution room for that year. So, if the 2025 contribution limit is &lt;strong&gt;$7,000&lt;/strong&gt;, you would now have &lt;strong&gt;$12,000&lt;/strong&gt; available to contribute in 2025.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will create a seperate blog post going more in depth about the TFSA as well as other type of accounts available in Canada (RRSP, FHSA, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&apos;t open a managed account&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead, open a self-directed account instead (this should be an option where you can select your own Stocks, ETFs, etc). The Halal Portfolio is now just a single ETF, &lt;strong&gt;WSHR&lt;/strong&gt;, and Gold. In my opinion, it’s not worth paying the extra 0.5% management fee to Wealthsimple when you can easily buy it yourself. However if you would like even more simplicity, you can opt for the managed account which will handle purchasing stocks for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine your TFSA contribution space&lt;/strong&gt; and figure out how much you can realistically invest by the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started investing in my early 20s, so I had accumulated a large contribution space (~$20k).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I needed to know how much I was going to contribute over the course of the year. I was new to investing and paranoid, so I wasn&apos;t comfortable putting in a large sum of money all at once (nor did I have $20k). Instead, I decided to contribute &lt;strong&gt;$50/week&lt;/strong&gt; into my TFSA. I was not worried about over contributing since the total I&apos;d invest over the year would be $2600, which is less than my contribution limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purchase investments with your now funded TFSA&lt;/strong&gt;. Now that you have money in your TFSA, you need to purchase investments so they can grow over time. If you had opted for the &lt;strong&gt;Managed Account&lt;/strong&gt; option in Step 2, you can skip this step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search up the stock/ETF you want to purchase. In this case, search up &lt;strong&gt;WSHR&lt;/strong&gt;. Click on it, and you should see a &lt;strong&gt;Buy&lt;/strong&gt; button. Click on it, and you should be able to input the amount you want to purchase and from which account you want to purchase it from (select TFSA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If your TFSA has $100 in it, and you want to buy a stock that is $150, you can still buy it since Wealthsimple allows you to purchase fractional shares. This means you can buy a portion of a stock/ETF if you don’t have enough money to buy a full share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build the habit&lt;/strong&gt; of investing regularly. The amount you put in weekly/monthly doesn’t matter as long as you don’t over-contribute. It’s just important to get started. This will help calm your nerves about the new process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it&apos;s not the focus of this post, it&apos;s important to remember that investing is a long-term game. The stock market can be volatile, and it&apos;s important to not panic when the market goes down. Instead, view it as an opportunity to buy more shares at a discount. Check out the concept of &lt;strong&gt;Dollar-Cost Averaging&lt;/strong&gt; for more information, and I will write up a post explaining this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there you go, you are now investing in your future in an Islamically-minded way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out my post on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2024-09-24-halal-investing/&quot;&gt;A Guide to Investing with Islamic Principals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for more information on my investing mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Guide to Investing with Islamic Principles]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Guide to Investing with Islamic Principles This guide is tailored towards young Muslim men and women starting their careers, but the…]]></description><link>https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-09-24-halal-investing/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-09-24-halal-investing/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;A Guide to Investing with Islamic Principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide is tailored towards young Muslim men and women starting their careers, but the advice can apply to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my first internship, it was the first time I made a substantial amount of money, and I didn’t know what to do with it. It would be irresponsible of me to just spend it, and I also learned that holding money in cash isn’t good because inflation would just decrease its value over time. So, I didn’t know what else to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/brian-pho/&quot;&gt;Brian Pho&lt;/a&gt;, taught me about investing in &lt;strong&gt;Exchange-Traded Funds (ETFs)&lt;/strong&gt;. ETFs are basically a collection of stocks all rolled into one ticker. This is safer than buying a single company stock because even giants (like Nortel or BlackBerry) can collapse, but it’s going to be armageddon if the entire economy collapses. At that point, money will have no value and only resources will matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mutual funds&lt;/strong&gt; are similar and are usually pitched to you by your local bank. They are a collection of stocks and &lt;strong&gt;bonds&lt;/strong&gt;, which offer a guaranteed payout. Bonds are essentially debt instruments: companies or governments borrow your money and agree to pay a fixed percentage return over time, which is guaranteed. While this can provide stability, the return is considered &lt;strong&gt;interest (Riba)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why Mutual Funds Are Not Shariah-Compliant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a Muslim, I couldn’t purchase traditional mutual funds from my bank because of &lt;strong&gt;Riba&lt;/strong&gt; (interest). Muslims are not allowed to partake in paying or receiving interest. Because mutual funds contain &lt;strong&gt;bonds&lt;/strong&gt; (which inherently involve interest payments), they are not permissible in Islam. Bonds are essentially banks/companies taking out loans from you. They borrow your money and agree to pay you a fixed % return, which is interest. This is why traditional mutual funds are not compliant with Islamic principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple rule of thumb is that if something is garunteed (there is no risk), then it is probably not halal. Other common terms that your bank might try to sell you no are GICs (Guaranteed Investment Certificates) and HISA (High-Interest Savings Accounts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why S&amp;#x26;P 500 Is Not Shariah-Compliant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common suggestion you might hear is to invest in the &lt;strong&gt;S&amp;#x26;P 500&lt;/strong&gt;, a collection of the 500 biggest public companies in the United States. It has historically had very good returns over the long run. However, as a Muslim, I cannot invest in this because it contains some companies that are not Shariah-compliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of companies in the S&amp;#x26;P 500 that are not Shariah-compliant include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JP Morgan Chase&lt;/strong&gt; (banking, interest-based revenue)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altria Group&lt;/strong&gt; (tobacco)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anheuser-Busch&lt;/strong&gt; (alcohol)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Las Vegas Sands&lt;/strong&gt; (gambling)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These companies are involved in businesses prohibited in Islam, such as tobacco, alcohol, banks (due to interest), and gambling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Halal Alternatives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, however, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sp-funds.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Factsheet-Dec-31-2020-SPUS-Broad.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPUS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a collection of all S&amp;#x26;P 500 companies minus the non-Shariah-compliant ones, catered specifically for Muslim investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my research, I came across &lt;strong&gt;Wealthsimple&lt;/strong&gt;, which offers managed portfolios that are Shariah-compliant and tailored towards Muslims. They published a great article about their &lt;strong&gt;Halal Portfolio&lt;/strong&gt;, which you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wealthsimple.com/en-ca/managed-investing/halal-portfolio&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m glad Wealthsimple recognized the growing Muslim demographic in Canada and created a portfolio to serve our needs. I have another blog post outlining &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2024-09-30-wshr/&quot;&gt;how to purchase your first halal ETF (WSHR) on WealthSimple&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in purchasing SPUS and other USD stocks/ETFs, I have another blog post outlining &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2024-10-01-spus-hlal/&quot;&gt;how to convert CAD to USD very cheaply on Questrade&lt;/a&gt;. Note this is a little bit more advanced and requires a bit more work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Future Topics to Cover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TFSA vs RRSP vs FHSA vs Non-Registered Accounts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crypto&lt;/strong&gt;: Should you have exposure to it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>