<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Sadat's Blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[A blog of things I've learned throughout my career.]]></description><link>https://sadat21.github.io/blog</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 05:02:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[A Guide to Investing with Islamic Principles]]></title><description><![CDATA[DRAFT POST IN PROGRESS A Guide to Investing with Islamic Principles This guide is tailored towards young Muslim men and women starting their…]]></description><link>https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-09-24-halal-investing/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sadat21.github.io/blog/2024-09-24-halal-investing/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;DRAFT POST IN PROGRESS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Guide to Investing with Islamic Principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide is tailored towards young Muslim men and women starting their careers, but the advice can apply to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my first internship, it was the first time I made a substantial amount of money, and I didn’t know what to do with it. It would be irresponsible of me to just spend it, and I also learned that holding money in cash isn’t good because inflation would just decrease its value over time. So, I didn’t know what else to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/brian-pho/&quot;&gt;Brian Pho&lt;/a&gt;, taught me about investing in &lt;strong&gt;Exchange-Traded Funds (ETFs)&lt;/strong&gt;. ETFs are basically a collection of stocks all rolled into one ticker. This is safer than buying a single company stock because even giants (like Nortel or BlackBerry) can collapse, but it’s going to be armageddon if the entire economy collapses. At that point, having a weak dollar might be the least of your worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mutual funds&lt;/strong&gt; are similar and are usually pitched to you by your local bank. They are a collection of stocks and &lt;strong&gt;bonds&lt;/strong&gt;, which offer a guaranteed payout. Bonds are essentially debt instruments: companies or governments borrow your money and agree to pay a fixed percentage return over time, which is guaranteed. While this can provide stability, the return is considered &lt;strong&gt;interest&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why Mutual Funds Are Not Shariah-Compliant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a Muslim, I couldn’t purchase traditional mutual funds from my bank because of &lt;strong&gt;Riba&lt;/strong&gt; (interest). Muslims are not allowed to partake in paying or receiving interest. Because mutual funds contain &lt;strong&gt;bonds&lt;/strong&gt; (which inherently involve interest payments), they are not permissible in Islam. Bonds are essentially banks/companies taking out loans from you. They borrow your money and agree to pay you a fixed % return, which is interest. This is why traditional mutual funds are not compliant with Islamic principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why S&amp;#x26;P 500 Is Not Shariah-Compliant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common suggestion you might hear is to invest in the &lt;strong&gt;S&amp;#x26;P 500&lt;/strong&gt;, a collection of the 500 biggest public companies in the United States. It has historically had very good returns over the long run. However, as a Muslim, I cannot invest in this because it contains some companies that are not Shariah-compliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of companies in the S&amp;#x26;P 500 that are not Shariah-compliant include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JP Morgan Chase&lt;/strong&gt; (banking, interest-based revenue)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altria Group&lt;/strong&gt; (tobacco)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anheuser-Busch&lt;/strong&gt; (alcohol)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Las Vegas Sands&lt;/strong&gt; (gambling)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These companies are involved in businesses prohibited in Islam, such as tobacco, alcohol, banks (due to interest), and gambling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Halal Alternatives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, however, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sp-funds.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/Factsheet-Dec-31-2020-SPUS-Broad.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SPUS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a collection of all S&amp;#x26;P 500 companies minus the non-Shariah-compliant ones, catered specifically for Muslim investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my research, I came across &lt;strong&gt;Wealthsimple&lt;/strong&gt;, which offers managed portfolios that are Shariah-compliant and tailored towards Muslims. They published a great article about their &lt;strong&gt;Halal Portfolio&lt;/strong&gt;, which you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wealthsimple.com/en-ca/managed-investing/halal-portfolio&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m glad Wealthsimple recognized the growing Muslim demographic in Canada and created a portfolio to serve our needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crash Course on What to Do&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s a quick step-by-step guide. I’ll dive into more detail in future blog posts if there is interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open a Wealthsimple account&lt;/strong&gt; using my referral code &lt;strong&gt;VZP-FW&lt;/strong&gt;. It’ll give both of us a small gift (as of writing, it’s $25 or $10,000 managed for free for a year).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open a TFSA account&lt;/strong&gt;. TFSA stands for &lt;strong&gt;Tax-Free Savings Account&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a special account where you don’t have to pay any tax on any gains made within the account. However, there is a limit on how much you can contribute. You unlock more contribution room on January 1st each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: If you turned 18 in 2023, your contribution room for that year would be $6,500. For 2024, the contribution limit has increased to &lt;strong&gt;$7,000&lt;/strong&gt;, giving you a total of &lt;strong&gt;$13,500&lt;/strong&gt; in contribution space if you haven’t yet contributed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check past contribution limits on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/services/tax/individuals/topics/tax-free-savings-account/contributions.html&quot;&gt;CRA website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always make sure you don’t exceed your contribution limit, or you’ll face fees from the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Withdrawals&lt;/strong&gt;: You can withdraw money from a TFSA without penalties, but you won’t be able to re-contribute that amount until the following year when the limit refreshes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: Let&apos;s say you have &lt;strong&gt;$10,000&lt;/strong&gt; in your TFSA, and in &lt;strong&gt;June 2024&lt;/strong&gt;, you decide to withdraw &lt;strong&gt;$5,000&lt;/strong&gt; for an emergency. You can withdraw the money without any penalties, but you cannot re-contribute that &lt;strong&gt;$5,000&lt;/strong&gt; until &lt;strong&gt;January 1st, 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, when your TFSA limit resets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your contribution room for 2024 was &lt;strong&gt;$7,000&lt;/strong&gt; (and you’ve already maxed it out), in 2025, you would get back the &lt;strong&gt;$5,000&lt;/strong&gt; you withdrew, plus the new contribution room for that year. So, if the 2025 contribution limit is &lt;strong&gt;$7,000&lt;/strong&gt;, you would now have &lt;strong&gt;$12,000&lt;/strong&gt; available to contribute in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&apos;t open a managed account&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead, open a self-directed account. The Halal Portfolio is now just a single ETF, &lt;strong&gt;WSHR&lt;/strong&gt;, and Gold. In my opinion, it’s not worth paying the extra 0.5% management fee to Wealthsimple when you can easily buy it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine your TFSA contribution space&lt;/strong&gt; and figure out how much you can realistically invest by the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I started investing in my early 20s, so I had a large contribution space, but I was nowhere close to maxing it out. I was new to investing and paranoid, so I didn’t feel comfortable putting in a large sum of money all at once. Instead, I automated a contribution of &lt;strong&gt;$50/week&lt;/strong&gt; into my TFSA. Wealthsimple lets you automate this process, so you don’t need to do it manually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build the habit&lt;/strong&gt; of investing regularly. The amount you put in weekly/monthly doesn’t matter as long as you don’t over-contribute. It’s just important to get started. This will help calm your nerves about the new process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like investing weekly because it allows me to &lt;strong&gt;dollar cost average&lt;/strong&gt; (a way to reduce risk by spreading out investments over time, which I’ll explain in a future blog post).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there you go, you are now investing in your future in an Islamically-minded way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Future Topics to Cover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norbert’s Gambit&lt;/strong&gt;: A way to invest in ETFs and companies traded in USD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TFSA vs RRSP vs FHSA vs Non-Registered Accounts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crypto&lt;/strong&gt;: Should you have exposure to it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[First Post]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is my first post on my new blog! How exciting! I'm sure I'll write a lot more interesting things in the future.]]></description><link>https://sadat21.github.io/blog/first-post/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sadat21.github.io/blog/first-post/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This is my first post on my new blog! How exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m sure I&apos;ll write a lot more interesting things in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>